Guide to the Burton Hall Union Democracy Oral History Collection OH 034
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Burton Hall Union Democracy Oral History Collection
1988-2001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
LaTour, Jane
OH 034
3 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 1 manuscript box, and 2 compact disk boxes.
Burton Hall was born in South Orange, New Jersey in 1929. He graduated from Williams College in 1951 and Yale Law School in 1954. Hall set up his own practice in 1960, and soon his work was almost entirely comprised of rank-and-file members suing to protect their democratic rights within their unions. He was one of the pioneer attorneys in developing the case law for the Labor-Management Reporting and Disclosure Act of 1959, also known as the Landrum-Griffin Act. His precedent-setting cases involved protection of the rights guaranteed by law in that section of the Act known as the "Bill of Rights" of union members. He represented rank-and-file members in numerous cases involving issues such as eligibility for running for union office, discipline against members for criticism of their leadership, and expulsion of union members for advocating radical political ideas. Jane Latour collected these interviews in her capacity as archivist of the Burton Hall Papers. The collection consists of interviews with rank and file insurgents, family members, representatives of union democracy organizations and others who worked with Burton Hall. The bulk of the interviews relate to Painters and Teamsters (Local 282) union reform efforts. The collection consists of audio recordings, transcripts, and contextual documentation.
Conditions Governing Access
Unless noted at the interview level, materials are open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Interviews were conducted for deposit at the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by Jane Latour (archivist for the Butron Hall Papers) and others between 1988 and 2001. The accession number associated with this collection is 1992.017.
Arrangement
Finding aid and compact disks are arranged alphabetically by last name of the interviewee. Master cassettes are arranged according to an archivist-devised numbering scheme which is partially chronological. This arrangement likely reflects the order that the tapes were added to the collection. Some numbers were repeated in the scheme.
Historical/Biographical Note
Burton Hall was born in South Orange, New Jersey in 1929. He graduated from Williams College in 1951 and Yale Law School in 1954. While in college and law school he was a member of the Food, Tobacco and Agricultural Workers Union in Camden, New Jersey, the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, Local 11, and the International Association of Machinists, Local 751, on the West Coast. He served in the U.S. Army from 1954 to 1956. He was admitted to the New York bar in 1957 and worked as a lawyer for a private firm and the Federal Aviation Agency before turning to labor law.
Burton Hall set up his own practice in 1960 as a labor lawyer. Soon his work was almost entirely comprised of rank-and-file members suing to protect their democratic rights within their unions. His office was located at 136 Liberty Street in Lower Manhattan. When the building was demolished to make way for the World Trade Center, he moved to 401 Broadway. Hall was one of the pioneer attorneys in developing the case law for the Labor-Management Reporting and Disclosure Act of 1959, also known as the Landrum-Griffin Act. His precedent-setting cases involved protection of the rights guaranteed by law in that section of the Act known as the "Bill of Rights" of union members. Thus he represented rank-and-file members in numerous cases involving issues such as eligibility for running for union office, discipline against members for criticism of their leadership, and expulsion of union members for advocating radical political ideas.
Scope and Contents
Jane Latour collected these interviews in her capacity as archivist of the Burton Hall Papers. The collection consists of interviews with rank and file insurgents, family members, representatives of union democracy organizations, and others who worked with Burton Hall. The bulk of the interviews relate to Painters and Teamsters (Local 282) union reform efforts.
The interviews were recorded on cassettes and have been digitized for preservation purposes. Some interviews have associated transcripts, interview notes, or summaries. There are also articles and other contextual documentation associated with certain interviews.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Labor unions -- Construction workers -- New York (State); Collective bargaining |z New York (State) |z New York.; Labor union democracy -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor union democracy |z United States.; Labor unions -- Corrupt practices -- New York (State) -- New York.; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades; International Brotherhood of Teamsters; Utility Workers Union of America. Local 1-2; Hall, Burton
- John Alfarone, Dec 29, 1994 and Jan 6, 1995 (Box 2, Cassette 12A-D, Box 3, Cd Alfarone 1-4, Box 1, Folder 1)
- David Barrish, Jul 26, 1993 and Jul 28,1993 (Box 2, Cassette 1A-B, Box 1, Folder 2, Box 3, Cd Barrish 1-2)
- Herman Benson, Feb 24, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3, Box 2, Cassette 9A-B, Box 3, Cd Benson 1-2)
- Carl Blum, Jul 27, 1993 (Box 2, Cassette 2A-F, Box 1, Folder 4, Box 3, Cd Blum 1-5)
- Mike Cotter, Jul 10, 1988 (Box 2, Cassette 16A-B, Box 3, Cd Cotter 1-2, Box 1, Folder 5)
- Charles Curd, Apr 29, 1995 (Box 2, Cassette 10, Box 3, Cd Curd 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
- Patrick Dolan, Seo 15, 2001 (Box 2, Cassette 20A-B, Box 3, Cd Dolan 1-2, Box 1, Folder 7)
  Scope and Content Note
  Interview regarding Utility Workers Union, Local 1-2.
- Robert Eckersdorf, May 2, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8, Box 3, Cd Eckersdorf 1-3, Box 2, Cassette 7A-C)
- Eric Franklin, Nov 1984 and Dec, 12, 1985 (Box 3, Cd Franklin 1-2, Box 1, Folder 9, Box 2, Cassette 14A-B)
  Recorded interviews on WBAI regarding Independent Association of Publishers and Employees, Inc. and Wall Street Journal.
- Daniel French, Oct 23, 1992, Sep 1, 1993, and Sep 4, 1993 (Box 3, Cd French 1-4, Box 2, Cassette 4A-D)
- James Geoghegan, Feb 17, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 10, Box 2, Cassette 17A-C, Box 3, Cd Geoghegan 1-4)
- Burton Hall Memorial Service, Dec 14, 1991 (Box 2, Cassette 13, Box 3, Cd Hall Memorial 1-2)
- Henry Hall, Nov 6, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 11, Box 3, Cd Hall 1, Box 2, Cassette 8)
- John N. Hayes, Jul 17, 1995 (Box 3, Cd Hayes 1-3, Box 2, Cassette 15A-B, Box 1, Folder 12)
- Ted Katsaros, Oct 4, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- L. Kudla / J. Carter, Nov 4, 1993 (Box 2, Cassette 5A-B, Box 3, Cd Kudla/Carter 1-2)
- Dr. Steve Levin, May 10, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 14, Box 3, Cd Levin 1, Box 2, Cassette 21)
  Interview regarding Mount Sinai Clinic.
- James McNamara, Dec 17, 1997 (Box 2, Cassette 24A-C, Box 1, Folder 15, Box 3, Cd McNamara 1-3)
  Interview taken by Stacy Sewell at Tamiment Library.
- Tom Moran, Apr 20, 2000 (Box 2, Cassette 19A-B, Box 4, Cd Moran 1-2, Box 1, Folder 16)
  Interview regarding Local 1-2, Utility Workers.
- Leon Olson, Apr 29, 1995 (Box 2, Cassette 11, Box 4, Cd Olson 1, Box 1, Folder 17)
- Richard Ostrowski, Dec 7, 2000 (Box 2, Cassette 18A-B, Box 1, Folder 18, Box 4, Cd Ostrowski 1-2)
- Frank Schonfeld, Dec 3, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19, Box 2, Cassette 8A-C, Box 4, Cd Schonfeld 1-5)
  Access Restrictions
  Interview is open for research, providing that the researcher follows the stipulation below, as agreed to in Schonfeld's release form for the interview:
  "The tapes are available for approved research purposes with the proviso that any allegation of possible organized crime association with regard to any individual will not be made public in the lifetime of the individual, unless the allegation has been proven in a court of law."
- Frank Schonfeld, Jan 7, 1988 (Box 2, Cassette 9A-C, Box 4, Cd Schonfeld 6-9, Box 1, Folder 19)
- Frank Schonfeld, Apr 4, 1988 (Box 2, Cassette 10A-B, Box 1, Folder 19, Box 4, Cd Schonfeld 10-11)
- Frank Schonfeld, Jan 21, 1994 and Oct 3, 1994 (Box 4, Cd Schonfeld 12-14, Box 2, Cassette 6A-B, Box 1, Folder 19)
- Arthur Schwartz, Esq., Sep 1, 2000 (Box 4, Cd Schwartz 1, Box 2, Cassette 22, Box 1, Folder 20)
  Interview regarding Local 1-2 Utility Workers.
- Nancy Stearns Esq., Dec 8, 2000 (Box 4, Cd Stearns 1-2, Box 1, Folder 21, Box 2, Cassette 23A-B)
  Interview regarding Local 1-2 Utility Workers Union.
- Mario Vozzo, Jul 28, 1993 (Box 4, Cd Vazzo 1, Box 2, Cassette 3)